A Guide to the Papers of Fredson Bowers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Fredson Bowers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12730
The collection is about 702 items, 2.5 Hollinger boxes and less than 1 linear foot.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
Fredson Thayer Bowers was born in New Haven, Connecticut on April 25, 1905. Although he was the only child of Fredson Eugene Bowers and Hattie May Quigley, he grew up with two half-sisters (the children of his mother's previous marriage) and a stepfather, Charles K. Groesbeck.
Bowers entered Brown University at age 16 after graduating from New Haven General High School in 1921. His study interests were in English literature and music, both of which he pursued with vigor. He was a member of Phi Beta Kappa and participated in a variety of literary, music and student activity clubs. He edited the school newspaper and served on the boards of student publications. He played the Hawaiian guitar, the saxophone and led a jazz band. On November 11, 1924, at age 19, while still an undergraduate, he married Hyacinth Adeline Sutphin, a Smith College graduate and member of a New York Social Register family.
Bowers graduated from Brown in 1925 and spent the next nine years at Harvard doing graduate study and raising a family. A son, Fredson, was born in 1927, a daughter, Joan, in 1931, and twin sons, Peter and Stephen, in 1934. Bowers taught English, tutored in modern languages and developed a passion for breeding, showing, judging and writing about Irish wolfhounds. He earned his Ph.D in February, 1934 and the next year went to England on scholarship.
In 1936, following an episode of marital problems that had led to a divorce, Bowers took an instructorship at Princeton. He taught freshman English and did editing work on Thomas Dekker until he accepted an offer from Dean James Southall Wilson to serve as acting assistant professor at the University of Virginia, which remained his home for the rest of his life. At the University of Virginia, Bowers taught English along with 17th and 18th century novels and a course in introductory bibliography. In 1942, he married Nancy Hale, and relocated with her to wartime Washington, D.C. where he served as a Naval Commander supervising the deciphering of enemy codes.
Bowers' impressive scholarship during his early years in Charlottesville resulted in his recognition as a preeminent authority of bibliographical analysis. His ideas and methods broke new ground and challenged established principles and methods in descriptive bibliography and textual criticism. In this period, he inaugurated the publication of Studies in Bibliography which he personally edited for more than 40 years and developed into a journal of worldwide repute. In 1949, he published Principles of Bibliographical Description, which became and remains a major resource in the history of bibliography. His prestigious lectures and the voluminous output of his published essays and research together with his activities on and leadership of professional associations marked him as a dynamic scholar in his field. As a teacher of boundless energy and as an active and innovative chairman and dean, Bowers built the English department at the University of Virginia into one of the best in the United States. Bowers still found time to teach summer courses at the University of Chicago and to pursue his hobbies: writing music reviews each week for the Richmond Times- Dispatch and publishing articles about his beloved wolfhounds and his philatelic interests.
During his later career years, Bowers turned his scholarship skills in textual criticism to editing the works of post-medieval writers. He published dozens of edited volumes (60 between 1960 and his death) creating distinct expressions of technique and methodology that became recognized among many as the "Bowers school of editing." He continued producing large numbers of essays, lectures and reviews beyond his retirement in 1975.
Throughout his notable career, Bowers was the recipient of numerous awards and recognitions. Among the many were honorary degrees from Clark and Brown Universities and the University of Chicago. He received the Gold Medal of the Bibliographical Society in London and his own University of Virginia recognized his many achievements with its highest honor, the Thomas Jefferson Award as well as two endowed chairs, the Alumni Professorship of English (1957-68) and the Linden Kent Memorial Professorship (1968-75, 1975-91 (Emeritus)). Bowers also held appointments to the Fulbright, Guggenheim, Rosenbach, Woodrow Wilson National and the Academy of Arts and Sciences fellowships. In 1974, Bowers was honored by his former Virginia and Chicago students at a retirement dinner and in 1985, on the occasion of his eightieth birthday, his colleagues organized an international conference on bibliography and editing in his name at the University of Virginia.
Nancy Hale, whose health had been failing for several years, died in 1988 and Bowers, who had also begun suffering with major health problems, died a few years later on April 11, 1991, at age 86. Following cremation, his ashes were buried next to the grave of Nancy Hale at Forest Hills Cemetery in Jamaica Plain, Boston.
Scope and Content
The collection consists mostly of editorial files from Fredson Bower's work on Stephen Crane and is from 1895 to 1973; 1993. There are mostly electrostatic photocopies about Stephen Crane, his works, and correspondence of his wife Cora, his friends, agents and his publishers including James Pinker, and Paul R. Reynolds. There are also articles about Stephen Crane and American Literature. The photocopies are from Dartmouth, University of Virginia, and mostly Columbia University. There is correspondence between Fredson Bowers and J. C. Levenson regarding the editing of "The Works of Stephen Crane."
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic.
Contents List
- 1967-1973; n. d. Articles, 45 items (Box-folder 1:1)
  "Some Notes on Harold Frederic in Ireland," "Stephen Crane's Dan Emmonds: A Case Reargued," "Stephen Crane and The Biographical Fallacy: The Cora Influence," "Last Essays," "Joseph Conrad Life and Letters," "Success Story," "The Crucible of Childhood," "Fame and Prejudice," "Unrecorded Parody of Stephen Crane," review of "The Works of Stephen Crane," by Fredson Bowers, "Fame and Prejudice," "Crane's 'Lines:' A Last Note on the Bookman," "Stephen Crane, Muckraker," "Stephen Crane At Brede," "The Fifth Man in 'The Open Boat," and "War Correspondents of 1860-5"
- 1974-1982; 1993 Correspondence of Dora Jean Ashe, 4 items (Box-folder 1:2)
  There are letters from Fredson Bowers and A. L. Rowse
- 1896 Correspondence of Sir James M. Barrie, 1 photocopy (Box-folder 1:3)
  The creator of Peter Pan wrote to the "Sign O' the Lanthorn' Club of New York regretfully declining to attend a dinner given in Crane's honor but praises Crane for "The Red Badge of Courage"
- 1969-1970 Correspondence of Fredson Bowers and Jack C. Levenson, 30 items (Box-folder 1:4)
- 1897 Correspondence of Willis Brooks Hawkins, 22 photocopies (Box-folder 1:5)
  There are letters from Amy Leslie to Willis Brooks Hawkins asking him for money and "Steve" [Stephen Crane] is mentioned
- 1968-1970 General Correspondence, 3 items (Box-folder 1:6)
  General correspondence including letters from Lillian B. Gilkes and Joseph Katz to Fredson Bowers
- 1973 General Correspondence, 16 items (Box-folder 1:7)
  Fredson Bowers corresponded with Ignas K. Skrupselis and other colleagues about Skrupselis' manuscript on William James
- n. d. Stephen Crane Collection at Columbia University, 10 items (Box-folder 1:8)
  There are finding aids and lists of materials related to Stephen Crane in the holdings at Columbia University
- n. d. Notes on Stephen Crane, 24 items (Box-folder 1:9)
  There are handwritten notes about Stephen Crane's life and work
- 1895-1907; n. d. Photocopies from Columbia University, 50 items (Box-folder 1:10)
  There are photocopies of correspondence from Cora and Stephen Crane to friends, family members and agents.
- 1895-1907; n. d. Photocopies from Columbia University, 100 items (Box-folder 1:11)
  There are photocopies of correspondence from Cora and Stephen Crane with friends, family members and agents.
- 1895-1907; n. d. Photocopies from Columbia University, 50 items (Box-folder 2:1)
- 1895-1907; n. d. Photocopies from Columbia University, 75 items (Box-folder 2:2)
- 1895-1907; n. d. Photocopies from Columbia University, 100 items (Box-folder 2:3)
- 1895-1907; n. d. Photocopies from Columbia University, 75 items (Box-folder 2:4)
- 1895-1907; n. d. Photocopies from Columbia University, 25 items (Box-folder 2:5)
  There are photocopies of correspondence from Cora and Stephen Crane with friends, family members and agents. Included is a copy of Stephen Crane's manuscript, "The Lavender Trousers."
- n. d. Photocopies from Columbia University, 15 items (Box-folder 2:6)
  The photocopies are of notes written by Stephen Crane while he was working on "The Ol' Ruddy" and other novels
- n. d. Photocopies from Columbia University, 20 items (Box-folder 2:7)
  There are photocopies of receipts and other financial information such as budget lists
- n. d. Photocopies from Dartmouth University, 3 items (Box-folder 3:1)
  The photocopies are of correspondence from Cora Crane to James Pinker regarding the selling of Crane's stories
- 1898 Photocopies from the Huntington Library, 1 item (Box-folder 3:2)
  There are photocopies of Stephen Crane's manuscript, "The Five White Mice"
- n. d. Miscellaneous photocopies, 11 items (Box-folder 3:3)
  There are photocopies of letters from Stephen Crane
- n. d. Photocopies from the University of Virginia, 22 items (Box-folder 3:4)
  There are copies of letters between Thomas Beer and the Crane family regarding accurate facts about Stephen Crane's life. There are also copies of manuscripts by Stephen Crane, titled "The Lover and the Tell Tale" and "Brer Washington's Consolation"